## JOSEPH S. HERNANDEZ

## DATA ENGINEER | DATABASE ADMINISTRATOR

▶ jshernandez05@gmail.com (760)505-4740 In linkedin.com/in/jshernandez05/ ☐ github.com/jshernandez05

#### **PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY**

Data professional and Military Veteran with Top Secret Security Clearance and 24 years of proven experience in supply chain analytics and information technology. A technical problem solver with comprehensive knowledge in database administration, system administration, leadership, and project management. Record of success in improving logistics and supply chain operations by combining technical expertise with data insights to drive process improvement and managerial decisions. Fast learner who quickly grasps and adapts to new concepts, technologies, and settings.

#### **SKILLS**

- Advanced SQL
- Python | R
- Linux
- Bash Scripting
- Airflow
- Data Warehousing
- MS Excel
- Tableau | PowerBI
- PostgreSQL | MySQL Leadership
- Google Cloud | AWS Team Building • Git | GitHub
- Docker
- Problem Solving
- Adaptability
- Project Management
- Customer Service
- Communication
- Presentation

#### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

## Naval Information Warfare Center - San Diego, CA System and Database Administrator

August 2018 – Present

- Managed fleet support center responsible for the technical support of 30 Linux servers and 60 aviation logistics databases to 15,000+ users.
- Resolved over 4,000 trouble tickets related to networking, server configuration, data pipelines, and database stored procedures minimizing system downtime and maintaining 99.97% operational readiness.
- Automated 65 routine trouble ticket resolutions utilizing python, bash, and SQL scripts reducing ticket closure time by 36%.
- Lead 36 large scale database server upgrade and data migration projects leading to enhanced system security and capabilities for 355 aviation logistics units across Naval Aviation Enterprise.
- Developed 3 python programs as interim solutions for broken stored procedures facilitating continued customer capabilities and system availability while eliminating 1000+ man hours of manual processing.
- Conducted 25 executive level briefs and presentations on software implementation benefits, project scopes, timelines, and status.

## United States Marine Corps - MCAS Beaufort, SC Supply Chain Analyst

April 2015 – August 2018

- Managed inventory of 14,580 stock items valued at \$350 Million with 100% validity.
- Built ETLs to ingest transactional data sets for 14,580 inventory line items from 6 databases to aid in analysis and support stock posture changes yielding a critical component fill rate of 95%.
- Created 2 data warehouses providing senior level management quick visibility of KPI's, metrics, and dashboards reducing time required to obtain information by 50%.
- Led an analysis tool development project which resulted in a deployment support order fill rate of 85% over a three-year period.
- Streamlined reverse logistics processing of non-repair components using descriptive, exploratory, and causal analysis reducing processing time by 16 hours.

### United States Marine Corp - Atsugi, Japan Air Logistics Cost Analyst

March 2013 – April 2015

- Devised 25+ custom reports and database views using SQL, Python, MS Excel, and MS Access.
- Developed and implemented a power bi based data model that automated cost analysis and visualized various metrics reducing processing time by 48 hours and providing \$4 Million in cost savings over two years.
- Constructed reusable scripts for data wrangling improving business process completion time by 10%.
- Planned and coordinated air cargo movement for over 200 Navy Air Logistics Office flights facilitating the movement of 500,000+ pounds valued at \$400 Million.

### United States Marine Corps – Camp Pendleton, CA Senior Logistics Manager

April 2011 - March 2013

- Directed warehouse operations for 47 personnel and an inventory valued at \$275 Million, employed to sustain peace time and wartime operations for 176 aircraft.
- Conducted analysis utilizing SQL and MS Excel to extract insights on 20 critical bit piece parts creating
  production and repair work stoppage enabling increased parts procurement and a 10-day turnaround time
  improvement.
- Identified 100+ database errors and corrected them utilizing DDL, DML, DCL, and TCL SQL commands.
- Created a MS Access database to automate SQL database queries and audit requirement validation resulting in 100% score on all internal and external audits.
- Received Department of the Navy Commendation for accomplishments.

# United States Marine Corps – Camp Dwyer, Afghanistan Container Management Officer

January 2010 – April 2011

- Spearheaded the establishment and use of a database to track inventory and location of 50,000 shipping containers throughout southern Afghanistan resulting in a \$350,000 reduction in carrier detention charges.
- Conducted cost benefit analysis resulting in the purchase of 2,752 carrier owned containers eliminating a projected \$1.25 Million in detention charges.
- Coordinated the movement of 1000+ plus containers from remote forward operating and patrol bases to ports of entry to meet contract and carrier timelines.
- Recognized by the Commanding General and awarded Navy Commendation for accomplishments.

## United States Marine Corps – MCAS Beaufort, SC Senior Logistics Manager

May 2008 - January 2010

- Reviewed, transferred, and accounted for \$500M+ in protected aircraft stock material to global destinations.
- Provided logistical support to customers by managing and coordinating 20 pack-ups for remote deployment with over 7,400 total items worth \$25M+.
- Managed the inventory of five Fleet Support Allowance packages with over 9,845 restricted stock items valued at \$38M and maintaining inventory at 100%.
- Conducted weekly demand analysis to adjust stock posture and allowances of wartime packages yielded a critical component fill rate of greater than 85%.

#### **EDUCATION**

Master of Science, Data Science | Eastern University, St. Davids, PA – 2023 (June) Bachelor of Science, Accounting | University of Maryland, Global Campus – 2022

#### **CERTIFICATIONS**

CNSS-4012 Senior Systems Manager | Information Assurance Associates
CNSS-4015 System Certifier | Information Assurance Associates
Top Secret Security Clearance | Department of Defense
Google Data Analytics Professional Certificate | Coursera
Lean Six Sigma Green Belt | Naval Aviation Enterprise